Guide to the Fausto Giaccone photographs and papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Fausto Giaccone photographs and papers
1966-2013
GEN MSS 1255
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.6
(17 boxes)
The collection consists of photographs, papers, and publications that document the work of Italian photojournalist Fausto Giaccone (1943-), from 1966 to 2013. The material includes Giaccone's reportage of social and cultural aspects of Europe, South America, and the Middle East, with an emphasis on political movements in Italy and Portugal from 1966 to 1986. The photographic materials in this collection consist of exhibition prints, work prints, contact sheets, and original slides for fifteen photo journalism assignments; prints for three exhibitions; and slides and work prints for two books, as well as a portfolio of color prints. The papers largely document the production of the book Una storia portoghese (Palermo: Randazzo, 1987), and include clippings and exhibition reviews. The papers also include exhibition catalogs, publications, and publicity material produced for various projects. Some of Giaccone's publications are also included with the collection.
Giaccone, Fausto, 1943-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 15 (CDs): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from L'Arengario Studio Bibliografico on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2014.
Fausto Giaccone (born 1943)
Fausto Giaccone is an Italian photographer and photojournalist whose work focuses on social movements and cultural issues in Europe, South America, and the Middle East. Born in Tuscany, Italy, in 1943, Giaccone grew up in Palermo and moved to Rome in the mid-1960s to study at the Valle Giulia School of Architecture at the University of Rome. Giaccone began his photojournalism career photographing the student protests at the University in March 1968, an event that became known as the Battle of Valle Giulia. Since the 1960s, Giaccone has worked as a photojournalist, photographing current events for Italian newspapers and other European publications. His subjects have included the Italian student movement of the late 1960s, the Palestinian Fedayeen in Egypt and Jordan, the aftermath of the Carnation Revolution in Portugal, and a survey of European architecture of the 21st century.
His publications include Una storia portoghese (Palermo: Randazzo, 1987); European Millenium Architecture with Roberto Collova (Vienna: Regina Maria Anzenberger, 2003); Volti di Cavallino Treporti (Florence: EDIFIR, 2012); and Macondo: The World of Gabriel Garcia Marquez (Rome: Postcart, 2013).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photographs, papers, and publications that document the work of Italian photojournalist Fausto Giaccone (1943-), from 1966 to 2013. The material includes Giaccone's reportage of social and cultural aspects of Europe, South America, and the Middle East, with an emphasis on political movements in Italy and Portugal from 1966 to 1986. The photographic materials in this collection consist of exhibition prints, work prints, contact sheets, and original slides for fifteen photo journalism assignments; prints for three exhibitions; and slides and work prints for two books, as well as a portfolio of color prints. The papers largely document the production of the book Una storia portoghese (Palermo: Randazzo, 1987), and include clippings and exhibition reviews. The papers also include exhibition catalogs, publications, and publicity material produced for various projects. Some of Giaccone's publications are also included with the collection.
Photographic projects documented in the collection include reportage of the 1968 student movement in Rome; Palestinian fedayeen in Jordan and Lebanon in 1968 and 1974; the 1981 protest march in Comiso, Sicily; music festivals in Europe; and village life in Southern Italy during the 1970s. Other subjects depicted include fishermen in Mazara del Vallo, Sicily; Paraguan Mennonites; and city and village life throughout Yugoslavia, 1987 to 1990. Highlighted in the collection is Una storia portoghese (A Portuguese Story), a project resulting from two visits Giaccone made to Portugal, in 1975 and 1986, to document rural life in the wake of the Carnation Revolution. Also highlighted in the collection are photographs of Colombia produced for Giaccone's 2013 book, Macondo: The world of Gabriel García Márquez (Rome: Postcard, 2013). Sets of prints are also included from three exhibitions: The Battle of Valle Giulia (American Academy in Rome, Rome, 2008), Viaggio nelle terre dei pastori (Nuoro, 1982), and Sicily 1968-1982 (Salemi, 1982).
Publications included with the collection include Una storia portoghese, the Italian and Portuguese editions; Macondo: The world of Gabriel García Márquez; and '68 Altrove.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Photographs, 1966-2010. II. Papers, 1975-2013. III. Printed material, 1987-2013.
Farmers -- Portugal -- Pictorial works; Fedayeen -- Pictorial works; Fishers -- Italy -- Sicily -- Pictorial works; Funeral rites and ceremonies -- Lebanon -- Beirut -- Pictorial works; Funeral rites and ceremonies -- Italy -- Rome -- Pictorial works; Mennonites -- Paraguay -- Pictorial works; Photojournalists -- Italy; Riots -- Italy -- Pictorial works; Sheepherding -- Pictorial works; Youth movements -- Italy -- Pictorial works; Beirut (Lebanon) -- Pictorial works; Bolivia -- Pictorial works; Bologna (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Comiso (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Couço (Santarém, Portugal) -- Pictorial works; Ecuador -- Pictorial works; Egypt -- Pictorial works; Isle of Wight (England) -- Pictorial works; Italy -- Pictorial works; Italy, Southern -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Jordan -- Pictorial works; Portugal -- History -- Revolution, 1974; Rome (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Sicily (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Yugoslavia -- Pictorial works; Yugoslavia -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Born digital -- Italy -- 20th Century; Clippings (information artifacts) -- Europe -- 20th Century; Exhibition catalogs -- Italy -- 20th Century; Gelatin silver prints -- Italy -- 20th Century; Inkjet prints -- Italy -- 20th Century; Photographs -- Italy -- 20th Century; Slides (photographs) -- Italy -- 20th Century; Photojournalists -- Italy -- 20th Century; Giaccone, Fausto, 1943-; García Márquez, Gabriel, 1927-2014 -- Homes and haunts; Isle of Wight Festival (3rd) -- Isle of Wight (England) -- 1970 -- Pictorial works
- Photographs, 1966-2010; Series I; 1.3; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized chronologically into 21 groups, according to project. The titles for projects were assigned by Giaccone. Within each group, the photographer separated original prints from later prints. The photographs in each project are arranged chronologically based on the date of image creation.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of photographic prints, including silver gelatin prints and inkjet prints; contact prints; and slides printed by Giaccone from 1966 to 2013 for various projects, assignments, exhibitions, and publications.
  - Rome 1966-1968: Student movement
    - 31 slides, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 4 contact sheets of the Battle of Valle Giulia, in the correct sequence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 18 contact sheets, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 2 contact sheets, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    - 4 contact sheets of the student movement in Rome, not in sequence, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    - 3 black and white coated paper prints, 1968
    - 8 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Rome, 1968, undated
    - 16 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken during the Battle of Valle Giulia in Rome, March 1, 1968, undated
  - Exhibition: The Battle of Valle Giulia, Rome 1968 (American Academy in Rome, July 2008)
    - 10 black and white later prints of the Battle of Valle Giulia, Rome, February-May 1968, 2008
    - 8 color inkjet later prints of the Battle of Valle Giulia, Rome, February-May 1968, 2008
    - 14 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Rome, 1968, undated
    - 1 exhibition poster from the American Academy in Rome exhibition 1968: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 2008
  - Middle East, summer 1968
    - Egypt: Cairo, Ismaïlia, Elouan, and Kafr-El Dawar
      - 4 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Egypt, 1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Egypt, 1968, undated
      - 2 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Egypt, 1968, undated
    - Jordan: Palestinian fedayeen from FPLP training
      - 2 black and white prints, 1968
      - 4 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Jordan, 1968, undated
      - 1 black and white inkjet later print from a photograph taken in Jordan, 1968, undated
  - Isle of Wight Festival, 1970
    - 24 slides, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 2 contact sheets, 1970
    - 15 black and white inkjet prints, 1970
  - Funeral of a fedayeen killed in combat in the Palestinian neighborhood of Chatila in Beirut, Lebanon, 1974
    - 3 contact sheets, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 9 black and white prints, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1 black and white later print from a photograph taken in Lebanon, 1974, circa 1980-1989
  - Una storia portoghese, 1975-1986
    - 18 inkjet contact sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 140 color slides, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 26 contact sheets, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - 35 black and white prints, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
    - 23 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Portugal, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 34-37)
    - 14 contact sheets, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - 12 black and white prints, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Portugal, 1975, undated
    - 1 black and white print, 1986
    - 3 inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Couço, 1986, 2014
    - 1 color inkjet later print, preparing for a sequence, Milan, 1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - 2 posters for Couço exhibition Una storia portoghese, 2006 April 25
  - Latin America, 1976
    - Bolivia
      - 28 slides, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 4 contact sheets, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - 16 black and white prints, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
      - 3 black and white prints, 1976
    - Ecuador
      - 1 contact sheet, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - 1 black and white print, 1976
  - Parco Lambro Festival, Milano, July 1976
    - 7 contact sheets, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - 10 black and white prints, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 1977
    - 27 contact sheets, 1977
    - 4 contact sheets, later prints from photographs taken in Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 1977, undated
    - 1 black and white poster of a photograph taken by Fausto Giaccone in Montalto di Castro, 1977, 2007
  - Southern Italy and islands, 1968-1981
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Palermo, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - 2 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Sardinia, 1968, undated
    - 2 black and white later prints from photographs taken in southern Italy, 1968-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sardinia, 1968-1969, undated
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sicilia, 1968-69, undated
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in southern Italy, 1968-1975, undated
    - 5 black and white prints taken in southern Italy, 1970-1980
    - 2 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Napoli, 1970, undated
    - 1 black and white print, Campagna, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - 2 black and white prints, Cilento, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sardegna, 1975, undated
    - 7 black and white prints, Calambria, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - 4 black and white prints, Sicilia, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - 2 black and white prints, Basilicata, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Color prints portfolio, eary 1980's
    - 50 color prints from color slides of various subjects, 1982
    - 25 color prints from color slides of various subjects, 1982
  - Protest march against the installation of cruise missiles at the Comiso Airport in Comiso, Sicily, 1981-1984
    - 1 black and white print from photograph taken in Comiso, October 11, 1981
    - 16 contact sheets, 1981-1984
    - 23 slides, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition 1982: Viaggio nelle terre dei pastori (Nuoro, Sardinia, 1982)
    - 18 color prints from slides, 1968-1981
    - 41 black and white prints, 1968-1981
  - Exhibition 1982: Sicily 1968-1982 (Salemi, Sicily, 1982)
    - 9 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sicily, 1968-1982
    - 44 black and white prints, 1968-1982
  - Enrico Berlinguer's funerals, Rome, June 13, 1984
    - 15 color slides, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fishermen community and first immigration from North Africa, Mazara del Vallo, Sicily, 1982
    - 6 inkjet contact sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 47 color slides, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Yugoslavia, 1987
    - 15 inkjet contact sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 124 color slides, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Yugoslavia, 1990
    - 9 inkjet contact sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 68 color slides, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Mennonites (Durango colony), Paraguay, 1990
    - 51 color slides, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Macondo: The world of Gabriel García Márquez, Colombia, 2013
    - 67 inkjet prints of photographs taken in Colombia, 2006-2010
  - Additional photographic prints
    - 3 black and white prints, 1968-1981
- Papers, 1975-2013; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series II is arranged chronologically.
  Series II includes textual and digital material compiled by Giaccone for his photographic projects and exhibitions. The largest groups of material document Una storia portoghese and Macondo: The world of Gabriel García Márquez. Documentation for these publications includes typewritten drafts with manuscript corrections and production dummies. Also included is a typewritten transcript of audio recordings made on August 31, 1975, during the Carnation Revolution. The text contains political discussions and dialogues between Portuguese farm workers and Captain Rodrigues of Movimento Farças Armadas. Also included are clippings and reviews for Una storia portoghese as well as exhibition catalogs and publicity material produced for Giaccone's photographic exhibitions.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 16 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Una storia portoghese
    - Transcription of recording made in Couço, August 31, 1975, circa 1975 (Box 14, Folder 118)
    - Photograph reproduction of poster for the first exhibition of work made in Couço, 1975, held by the architecture faculty in Palermo, April 26, 1977, undated (Box 14, Folder 119)
    - Fausto Giaccone text about cooperatives in Couço, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 120)
    - L'illustrazione Italiana, Anno VI, Numero 34, 1986 September (Box 14, Folder 121)
    - Antonio Tabucchi letter to Fausto Giaccone with his translation in Portuguese of prologue to Una storia portoghese, 1987 March 3 (Box 14, Folder 122)
    - Fausto Giaccone original texts written for Una storia portoghese, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 123)
    - Original layout for Una storia portoghese, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 124)
    - Original invitiation cards for exhibitions of Una storia portoghese, 1987-2006 (Box 14, Folder 125)
    - Reviews and clippings, circa 1987-2009 (Box 14, Folder 126)
    - Interview with Antonio Tabucchi published in Expresso, 1987 April 25 (Box 14, Folder 127)
    - Sandokan, Anno III, Numero 4, 1999 May (Box 14, Folder 128)
    - Review printed in Journal de Letras, Artes e Ideias, Ano XIX, N. 754, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 129)
    - Catalog for the Festival Sete Sóis Sete Luas 1993-1999, 2000 (Box 14, Folder 130)
    - Photographic reproduction, inkjet print, of Lotta Continua, September 26, 1975 issue, which first published the photographs taken by Fausto Giaccone in Couço, 2004
    - Die Tageszeitung, 2004 April
      In commemoration of the 30th anniversary of the Portuguese Carnation Revolution, Die Tageszeitung published five photographs from Una storia portoghese, printing one photograph a day over the course of a week.
    - Diario, Anno V, Numero 3, 2005 August 5 (Box 14, Folder 131)
    - Noticias Magazine, Numero 726, 2006 April 23 (Box 14, Folder 132)
    - A Reforma Agrária no Couço: Reencontro com uma História Portuguesa, booklets made by Inês Marques Cardoso, curator of the exhibition held in Couço, April 2006, 2006 April (Box 14, Folder 133)
    - Texts for Una storia portoghese by Fausto Giaccone, undated; 1 (Box 15, Folder 138)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Pages from Una storia portoghese, undated; 1 (Box 15, Folder 139)
  - Promotional material for Fausto Giaccone photograph exhibitions, 1982-2013 (Box 14, Folder 134)
  - American Academy in Rome, School of Fine Arts booklet, 2008 (Box 14, Folder 135)
  - Exhibition material for 1968: The Battle of Valle Giulia at the American Academy in Rome, 2008 (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - Production dummy for Macondo showing the first sequence of photographs, 2010 October (Box 14, Folder 137)
- Printed material, 1987-2013; Series III; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Series III is arranged chronologically by publication date.
  Series III includes copies of publications represented throughout the collection. Also included is '68 Altrove, a catalog of a solo exhibition chronicling Giaccone's early years as a photojournalist.
  - Giaccone, Fausto. Una storia portoghese. Palermo: Randazzo, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Giaccone, Fausto. Uma história portuguesa. Palermo: Randazzo, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Giaccone, Fausto. '68 Altrove. Fidenza: Grafica Malvisi, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 142)
  - Giaccone, Fausto. Macondo: The world of Gabriel García Márquez. Rome: Postcard, 2013 (Box 17)
- Oversize, 2.2; (10 boxes)
  - Rome 1966-1968: Student movement, 3 black and white coated paper prints (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 55)
  - Rome 1966-1968: Student movement, 8 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Rome, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Rome 1966-1968: Student movement, 16 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken during the Battle of Valle Giulia in Rome, March 1, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 57-59)
  - Exhibition: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 10 black and white later prints of the Battle of Valle Giulia, Rome, February-May 1968, 2008 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 60-61)
  - Exhibition: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 8 color inkjet later prints of the Battle of Valle Giulia, Rome, February-May 1968, 2008 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 62)
  - Egypt, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Egypt, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 63)
  - Egypt, 2 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Egypt, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 64)
  - Jordan, 2 black and white prints, 1968 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 65)
  - Jordan, 4 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Jordan, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 66)
  - Jordan, 1 black and white inkjet later print from a photograph taken in Jordan, 1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 67)
  - Exhibition: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 14 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Rome, 1968, undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 68-70)
  - Exhibition: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 1 exhibition poster from the American Academy in Rome exhibition 1968: The Battle of Valle Giulia, 2008 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 71)
  - Isle of Wight Festival, 2 contact sheets, 1970 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 72)
  - Isle of Wight Festival, 15 black and white inkjet prints, 1970 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 73-75)
  - Lebanon, 1 black and white later print from a photograph taken in Lebanon, 1974, circa 1980-1989 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 76)
  - Una storia portoghese, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Portugal, 1975, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 77)
  - Una storia portoghese, 1 black and white print, 1986 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 78)
  - Una storia portoghese, 3 inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Couço, 1986, 2014 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 79)
  - Photographic reproduction, inkjet print, of Lotta Continua, September 26, 1975 issue, which first published the photographs taken by Fausto Giaccone in Couço, 2004 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 80)
  - Die Tageszeitung, 2004 April 15-2004 April 21 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 81)
  - Una storia portoghese, 2 posters for Couço exhibition Una storia portoghese, April 25, 2006 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 82)
  - Bolivia, 3 black and white prints, 1976 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 83)
  - Ecuador, 1 black and white print, 1976 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 83)
  - Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 27 contact sheets, 1977 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 84-85)
  - Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 4 contact sheets, later prints from photographs taken in Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 1977, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 86)
  - Rome, Bologna, and Montalto di Castro, 1 black and white poster of a photograph taken by Fausto Giaccone in Montalto di Castro, 1977, 2007 (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 87)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 2 black and white inkjet later prints from photographs taken in Sardinia, 1968, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 88)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sardinia, 1968-1975, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 89)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sicilia, 1968-69, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 90)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in southern Italy, 1968-1975, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 91)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 5 black and white prints taken in southern Italy, 1970-1980 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 92)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 2 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Napoli, 1970, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 93)
  - Southern Italy and islands, 3 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sardegna, 1975, undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 94)
  - Protest march in Comiso, 1 black and white print of photograph taken in Comiso, October 11, 1981 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 95)
  - Protest march in Comiso, 16 contact sheets, 1981-1984 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 96)
  - Additional photographic prints, 3 black and white prints, 1968-1981 (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 97)
  - Color prints portfolio, 50 color prints from color slides of various subjects, 1982 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 98)
  - Color prints portfolio, 25 color prints from color slides of various subjects, 1982 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 99)
  - Exhibition 1982: Viaggio nelle terre dei pastori, 18 color prints from slides, 1968-1981 (Box 11 (Oversize), Folder 100)
  - Exhibition 1982: Viaggio nelle terre dei pastori, 41 black and white prints, 1968-1981 (Box 11 (Oversize), Folder 101)
  - Exhibition 1982: Sicily 1968-1982, 9 black and white later prints from photographs taken in Sicily, 1968-1982 (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 102)
  - Exhibition 1982: Sicily 1968-1982, 44 black and white prints (Box 12 (Oversize), Folder 103)